he
a
[Music]
hello good day and good evening
everybody I hope you're all doing great
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask Abhijit show today is the science
physics astronomy Etc Edition I hope
you're all doing great before we begin
as usual let me greet those of you who
are on the live chat let us see who all
is there I can see rajat Chopra I can
see Ashish Kumar Akash sual Ms SB
AR Ashish vishwakarma prna jvi Banda
Panda hello toi rala a sarak Singh Omer
hello animish hello Namaste dungar Singh
Chan hello sidhant Singh Chan hello
Malik say hello Sigma good evening
geopolitical Dubai hello Ragu rakshasi
Raj ADI takur pan Kumar Singh B NAD
droni Amar Chri Sachin G Harish akshai
shind
vishaka ban Bora
sagur dog pray Kumar Akay shind rakshasi
Etc vikrant animish Prat Arya aush
threat Ripper one unar bitupan AJ Rahul
meditation and relaxation
Ashish shivanu Samar Pand hello Shri ra
moan and lots lots of other people
dungar Singh Chan says Rajasthan may
meet up Koo okay let's try and do
that okay so we're going to take a bunch
of questions as always but before that I
have an announcement so we those of you
who are planning to attend tomorrow's
live stream it is unfortunately being
moved to Monday I have uh been invited
to prime minister modi's Inauguration
tomorrow so I'm going to have to attend
that obviously so tomorrow's live stream
will happen on Monday 9:00 p.m. on on
Monday not tomorrow so yeah one
announcement so who else let me briefly
greet some more people Aura nikil APS
talks
ainka Shri Harish Shri har gutam animish
SW Mishra hello uh Disciples of Mind
anul somat Chi Sammy Point Hitman spy
Shashi super saan sins and everybody
else all right all right all right okay
enough greeting greetings to everyone
now let's take some questions so I'm
going to take a a number of question
questions maybe 10 15 questions I will
take from the comments and then at the
end I will take as many as possible from
the live chat so that's going to be at
the end in the second half of today's
session so I'm going to keep it maybe 60
60 40% 60% from the comments and 40%
from the live chat that sort of thing
that's what I shall do today okay what
are the questions that we
have okay we begin with swapnil mishra's
question the question is what what was
the great unconformity time period
during which a huge chunk of the Earth's
paleontological timeline disappeared
okay I hope I haven't taken this
question before but anyway let's take it
so this is a question about geology
about natural history like the hashtag
says the hashtag over here Natural
History it's a geological question so
the Earth as we know has
sedimentation and sediments naturally
Depo get deposited on the crust of the
earth and the in the bottoms of bottom
of the oceans through natural processes
and this typically takes uh millions of
years so if we and and over over time
because of geological processes these
sediments and these formations the there
is upheaval geological upheaval and
these eventually break out through the
surface of the Earth and lots of
mountains if you go to the Himalayas you
will see lots of sedimentary layers you
know layer upon layer upon layer in each
layer typically is it represents a time
period of 10 of thousands of years
sometimes hundreds of time thousands of
years and a one foot two foot thick
layer of multiple sediments could be
several million years so that's how it
happens now and we can date the
sediments that this layer of sediment
these these particular sediments they
date from what time period and so on
there are various means and ways and
means of doing that so we can determine
at what level which
sediment uh existed was was formed so if
you want to see what sediments look like
let me put that on the screen so that
those of you are who are not aware will
get an understanding
okay so Earth sedi
sediment so what do sediments look like
so see you will see rocks in mountains
and Hills that have these layers so each
of these layers generally represents a
sediment that is that is Thousands maybe
tens of thousands maybe millions of
years old
and you will see this all over the place
I'm I'm sure everybody is familiar with
such sediments and you can see that
there are people there are people
standing on top of this formation and
below that there are sediments that
would go back hundreds of thousands of
millions maybe billions of years at
times and you can see that each sediment
every every stratum of sediment has
different characteristics different
colors and so on so this is a snapshot
into the deep history of the planet
itself
and you will often find uh fossils
within sediments some sediments have uh
shocked quartz and iridium which which
is the indicator of a significantly
large impact event like the last impact
event Extinction the chick Shob event
that happened about 66 million years ago
and you discover if you go back that at
that particular point in time in
sediments you will discover iridium and
you will discover shocked quarts and you
will discover many other things like SP
and all that so that tells you that
something drastic happened at the time
so that is what sediments are now what
is the great unconformity time period it
is a it is essentially an absence of
sediments from a certain period in our
planet's history so if you go back if
you if you go to places like the Grand
Canyon in North America which is
currently part of the us and so on you
will find all these exposed sediments on
the surf surfaces of the hills and
various formations and you will find
that certain time periods are missing
there's a significant missing time
period between half a billion to 1.2
billion years that sort of time period
and for that time period which begins if
we start going backwards from today it
starts about 530 540 million years
before today and it goes all the way
back to maybe a billion a billion and a
half years before today so that gap of
time is missing in the sediments and you
find this in various parts of the planet
not just at the Grand Canyon and that is
the great UNC Conformity missing
evidence I mean missing missing
sediments of the earth of the Earth's
natural history so that's the Great
unconformity and the question is why is
this time period missing from all these
sediments why don't we have layers
pertaining to that time period and we
don't quite have answers we don't quite
have have the answer to why is that time
period missing from the sedimentary
history of the planet it's a mystery and
there there are possible solutions that
have been proposed maybe there was a lot
of erosion or whatever in the time
period which is why the sediments could
not form and they could not settle down
in the bottoms of the oceans lot of
churn of some kind so we don't quite
have the answers right now but that is a
big mystery so there's Mysteries not
just in theoretical physics when it
comes to Dark Matter Dark Energy all
that stuff and much more there's
Mysteries when it comes to the history
of our own Planet itself lots of
mysteries when it comes to Earth's
natural history right so this is one of
those Mysteries and there are many many
more histories the origin of life is a
big mystery but the great unconformity
that is a missing it's it's a gap in our
uh in the hard history of the planet the
siment that those layers are missing and
we don't quite know why they are missing
so yeah that's what it is so that's the
question we begin with what's the next
question geopolitical dub asks a
question about volcano okay what if all
trash all plastic waste Etc was thrown
into volcano let's say we start throwing
all the trash all the plastic waste
everything into volcanos what will
happen because trash is a problem
garbage and waste is a problem we know
there are the oceans are getting choked
with plastic there are gigantic
you know trash repositories in the
oceans entire Island sized and and
almost small continents sized uh you
know regions in the in the Pacific Ocean
where they just garbage everywhere it
all just it all accumulates because of
the because of the currents of the ocean
and so on so there is a huge problem
this plastic and various other garbage
very various other trash that we human
beings produce what do we do with it
shall we dump it into the volcanos now
in case you all don't know what a
volcano looks like let me put that on
the screen uh one second give me a
second let
me so what is a volcano is the question
right so volcano
is is this thing here
that's
volcano so volcano is a mountain it's
essentially a mountain that that is a
portal into the deep
Nether world beneath the surface of the
planet and the magma layer comes into
contact with the atmosphere and it spews
out lava and the lava accumulates in the
form of these conical conical mountains
and sometimes you have dormant or
dormant or extinct volcanoes which leave
behind lakes in this manner and so on
this is a volcano so what if we take all
the trash all the plastic waste all of
that which we don't need and maybe which
we are not able to recycle what if we
just dump it into two volcanoes what
happens and that's a I would say it's a
good question it's a legitimate question
what happens why not do this so what's
so here's what happens let's say you
take plastic now plastic is a byproduct
of uh of hydrocarbons right uh to make
plastic how do we manufacture plastic it
is something that is manufactured from
processing hydrocarbons essentially oil
petroleum oil so it's a petroleum
byproduct there are certain processes
that we uh that we make the petroleum
undergo and plastic is a byproduct of
that so plastic essentially is a carbon
compound a hydrocarbon most likely I'm
not sure what the chemical structure the
chemical composition is but there's
carbon in there and plastic is non
biodegradable so let's say you take
plastic and you dump it let's say you
take 100 tons of plastic and you dump it
into a gigantic volcano there are such
volcano that you can do that in what
happens the volcanoes the lava is at an
extremely high temperature it is molten
rock so it's going to be hundreds of
degrees Celsius maybe more okay so you
dump plastic in there the plastic will
immediately ignite it will catch fire
it's it plastic is
reasonably less dense significantly less
dense than than molten rock so plastic
will float on the lava and it will melt
and it will burn so when plastic Burns
it's going to emit all kinds of carbon
suit carbon dioxide maybe carbon
monoxide and various other chemicals and
they're going to go out into the
atmosphere so that's not what you want
you want to reduce the carbon emissions
but by dumping plastic into a volcano
you're going to ignite the plastic it's
going to burn and bubble and steam and
all of these gases that are output from
that will go into the atmosphere and
it's mainly carbon products carbon based
gases like carbon dioxide and whatever
else is part of the plastic that you're
dumping in there so that's not a good
idea the plastic all that trash will not
simply sink below the surface it'll all
burn so instead of doing that you may
just incinerate all this garbage it's
it's going to have the same effect as
incinerating garbage and Inc
incinerating garbage is a very bad idea
we know that I mean there are Parts
there are various parts of the world
where instead of processing or recycling
garbage people governments just
incinerate the garbage essentially burn
it and what that does it creates this
horrible smog this Haze in the
atmosphere there are I'm sure there are
Indian cities when you're Landing you
don't see the city you just see a layer
of haze well that's what it create
creates so dumping plastic waste and
other kinds of waste inside volcano is
going to cause that effect it's going to
create that problem it's the same thing
as incinerating garbage and that is not
an environment friendly exercise or or
activity so that's why it's not a good
idea and obviously volcanos are unstable
and how do you take the hundreds of tons
of garbage all the way to the mouth of a
volcano what if it crumbles and you also
go in there you don't want to do that so
overall it's not very practical and even
if it were to be practical it is not a
very good idea because it's going to
release tremendous amounts of carbon
into the atmosphere and contribute
further to the climate change the human
mediated climate change which is is in
addition to the Natural climate change
which has always been happening all
right okay uh Vishal Kumar says what is
fire how is it produced and why is it
produced fire I think we all know what
fire looks like I don't think I have to
Google and put images of fire but let's
just do it just in case shall we let's
put images of fire on the screen
fire so this is what fire is
right this is what fire
is so Flames we are all familiar with
flames match sticks you know gas that
people use gas uh pipelines and you use
that for cooking purposes and so on and
Flames come in various colors depending
on the temperature and what you're
burning and so on and so forth that is
fire now this is a very good question
actually Vishal Kumar asks what is fire
I mean that's a very basic question very
fundamental question and I'm I'm sure
all kids of this question that this
thing that we see what is it what is
fire I remember when I was a kid I had a
cat I've always had cats as a kid so I
had this cat and he was he was a kitten
so he was like an adolescent from a
human perspective he would have been a
13 or 14 year old so this cat the when I
was a kid there used to be power
failures in India so there's a power
failure and there was a candle that we
had put up on the floor
so this cat he sees this flame and he's
curious you know kids are curious and
he's a kitten so he's curious so he goes
all all the way to the flame his he puts
his nose in the flame and sniffs it and
then he jumps six feet high in the air
and I promise you he would have never
done that again that's how we learned so
that's so even cats are curious about
what is this let me go and sniff it yeah
so the question is what's what is fire
and that's a very good question so fire
is not just a chemical reaction it's
also a physical reaction well it's it's
an oxidation process a very rapid and
exothermic oxidation Pro process which
so what is oxidation it is a chemical
reaction between something which is the
fuel and oxygen which is part of the
atmosphere so if you create a vacuum if
you if you
evacuate a box and you remove all the
air from it you can't have a flame in
there you can't burn anything there no
matter what you do okay so fire is a
rapid oxidation process which means it's
an exothermic chemical reaction
exothermic means it gives off light and
heat okay so the reaction products are
the what is produced by this reaction is
light heat and other reaction produced
it's an exothermic chemical reaction
which is also called combustion so
what's the chemistry of fire so first of
all what are the components what goes
into creating fire let's break it down
first of all we have fuel or what what
is called reactants so wood paper uh
gasoline petroleum whatever you want to
call it methane hydrogen gas okay this
is the reactant this is this is this is
the substance that burns or gets
oxidized that is number one and secondly
you have an oxidizer which is typically
oxygen from the air but you can also use
let's say in Rocket Fuel something like
uh hydrogen peroxide or something like
that so that can also work as an
oxidizer but from our perspective we'll
just talk about the oxygen in the air so
you have the reactants which are the
fuel and the oxygen and then you have
products so what comes out of the fire
so we have carbon dioxide let's say
you're burning wood the typical products
of this of this chemical reaction are
going to be carbon dioxide water also
and heat and light because you can sense
the heat you can see the light okay so
so that's that's the chemical reaction
you're going to have fuel plus oxygen
and you're going to induce this chemical
reaction by by applying heat by giving
it a source of heat and it gives our
carbon dioxide water and heat and light
okay now what are the stages of this
reaction this combustion reaction first
you have
ignition so you have seen ISRO in SpaceX
videos 10 9 8
all the way to zero LIF off normal love
the aent just love it we own that so you
will see that when you're about to reach
zero the fuel is being emitted from the
rocket whether it's a pslv or lmv which
whichever and suddenly there's a spark
and then the fuel ignites and whoosh the
flame comes out and then it propels the
rocket upwards right so that is ignition
the process of fire we breaking it down
here okay so it begins the process
begins when the fuel reaches what is
called its ignition temperature every
fuel has a different ignition
temperature plastic will have a
different ignition temperature wood for
various kinds of wood the ignition
temperature will be different for paper
it will be different for whatever else
it'll be different for various gases
it'll be different and so on so once the
fuel reaches the ignition temperature
that's when ignition happens and what
happens in ignition there are chemical
bonds Within the fuel molecules and
these will break because of the ignition
temperature and then they will start
reacting with oxygen that is ignition
the spark has been lit and the
fire is it just begins then the flame
will propagate so as the reaction this
ignition as this EXO as this oxidation
reaction progresses the heat generated
by the combustion will
sustain the reaction so now you don't
need need any more outside uh you don't
need any heat from outside anymore now
that the flame is on it's going to keep
on propagating and sustaining it's kind
of a chain reaction so the combustion
will continue to propagate and continue
it's a chain reaction combustion is a
chain reaction which means that the heat
generated by the reaction provides
enough energy to sustain the reaction as
long as fuel and oxidizer are both
present okay and then we can talk about
the physics of the fire so the are
various kinds of heat transfer which is
combustion and convection which means
the transfer of heat by movement of
fluids typically gases conduction means
direct contact which means you know two
substances in contact with each other
there is radiation as well transfer of
heat in the form of electromagnetic rad
waves then there is the emission of
light because we see that flame is it
produces light so there are two ways in
which flame produces light I mean we can
think of two ways one is black body
radiation the heated gases they emit
light due to a process called black body
radiation in which objects emit lights
of various frequencies or colors based
on their temperature and then you also
have excitation of molecules which means
the electrons in the atoms of the
burning material get exited to a higher
energy State higher energy level and
then they come down to the ground state
by releasing photons of Light which is
light itself of various colors so that
is a that is fire I've I think I've
really broken it down and uh so you need
a heat Source you need fuel fuel will
react with oxygen it decomposes it
breaks down into various other compounds
various things you can have soot that
comes out of it we can have uh soot you
can have volatile compounds which again
react with oxygen and so on so that is
what fire is and fire can come in
different colors depending on what
you're burning if you
burn if you burn sodium it produces fire
of I me you know you have spectrography
spectroscopy in which you have uh white
light can be broken down into various
Spectra we look at the Spectra of stars
and you can burn the same things to
produce the same colors that you have in
the spect of star so if you burn sodium
you burn magnesium Etc you will have
lights of different colors depending on
which atom it is and what are the energy
levels between which the electrons are
going up and coming down and so on so
that is what fire is you can you can do
a weekl long seminar on fire actually
that's how that's how come complicated
and interesting this very
straightforward mundane processes it's a
complicated interplay of chemistry as
well as physics chemical reactions and
physical processes oxidation of fuel you
need an O oxidizer there are there are
there's light emission through
exothermic reactions and so on that is
fire very interesting question and I I
wish that when kids ask these questions
they are not told to shut up and
somebody actually gives an answer to
this to to this question anyway good
question okay geopolitical duas say how
do windmills
work and how much how strong of an
energy can a windmill generate windmills
so a windmill okay let's go to Google
and and see what a windmill looks like
okay we'll go to blank Google and say
Wind
Mill
windmill we got an
image nope nope Google search images a
windmill so this is the windmill I'm
sure we've all seen them we've had
historically we had these smaller
windmills this is something that you
would see in Don kot Don quiot and Sano
Panza that that story that's what
ancient European windmills would look
like this sort of thing and then you
have modern windmills that you will see
all across the hills and everything if
you are in India there are lots of hills
and the Western GS and wherever else
that you will see mountains and Hills
that have hundreds of windmills placed
at top them on the slopes wherever it's
easy to catch uh wind so this is what a
windmill looks like okay so it's
essentially an object it's a machine
very simple machine you have a stand as
you can see there's a stand on which
there are these turbine blades
usually three three blades and the
blades are uh configured in such a
manner that they will catch the wind and
the wind will make the entire
Contraption go around okay so it going
to it's going to move in this circular
fashion so that's what it looks like now
how does a windmill work so once again
let's go to the image a windmill let's
say diagram
right diagram so what are the
constituent Paths of a windmill okay
there are various names so we have the
blades the turbine blades or rotor
blades let's call them okay and the wind
makes these blades turn now there is a a
shaft Which con connects the the blades
the blade apparatus to a gearbox and the
gearbox will will will then
turn uh this this
system and there is a generator with
with copper coils or whatever and
essentially what it does is it it
produces electricity through
electromagnetic induction that's what it
does so you will learn in
electromagnetism that uh moving magnets
when magnets move they generate an
electric current and when electricity
moves it also generates a magnetic field
electromagnetism is is all about
electric and magnetic fields so through
electric
induction the this this object this
machine generates elect
electricity
and it depends how much energy how much
electricity not energy
electricity uh a windmill generates
depends on the size it depends on the on
the size of the turbine on the size of
the
entire not the turbine the
blades it also depends on the size of
the entire windmill it also depends on
the weather conditions the wind
conditions and all that
and so on so generally when it comes to
a windmill once the speed of the blades
of the turbine it reaches 5 to 10
kilometers per hour that's generally
when it starts generating electricity
and I think if it reaches 2025 or Beyond
it's going to shut off automatically
just for
safety and so a windmill that is used
let's say privately in a home or in a
yeah let's say a private windmill a
private wind turbine will
generate electricity in the kilowatt
hour range but commercial and Industrial
wind turbines which are like the giant
ones that we see from far away from
aircraft and all those will generate
electricity in in the megawatt hour
range and there is an energy capacity
also for each wind
turbine which is a dimensionless number
it's a fraction 0.1 to to 1.0 uh 1.0 is
not not attainable so it's generally
0.25 to 0.5 0.6 and that tells you how
much how efficient the wind windmill is
so that's what it is it's a
very complicated engineering subject but
the fundamental basic simple principle
is that it generates electricity through
a phenomenon called
electric induction electromagnetic
induction that's what it is so it's it's
essentially free energy
wind energy comes from the sun okay you
have the planet half of it is dark half
of it is is in sunlight at any given
point in time so the half of the planet
which is which is experiencing sunlight
is going to be warmer and the half of
the planet which is currently dark night
time it's going to be cooler so you're
going to have a warm side and a cool
side of the planet and when you have hot
and cold then there's going to be
currents of air because cooler air is
heavier hotter air is lighter so cooler
air will flow towards the hotter side
and so on so there are these currents of
air that are generated that's how wind
is generated in the atmosphere of the
earth and there are low pressure areas
high pressure areas and so much it's
very
complicated trillions of parameters I
would imagine that's why you need
supercomputers to to predict weather
patterns so that's how wind is generated
and the wind is generated because of the
heat that's coming from the Sun so it's
free energy so it's good to have to to
harness that because that uh is great
you don't have to burn fossil fuels to
generate that energy of course it is not
very reliable wind can stop wind can
stop and start and it's not always
reliable but it's good to have this so
that's what windmills are and that's how
it
works okay Aditi says this question is
important to me please tell me about
palm oil I have heard of it being
injurious to human health if not for
human consumption what good can palm oil
serve can it act as a fuel in
manufacturing or for industrial purposes
or farm animal raising sector also what
is it scope especially related to India
I'll be grateful okay thank you so uh
palm oil is the question now what do we
do about that so palm oil is there is a
tree a plant called the palm palm tree
and palm oil is generated from the
fruits it is it is extracted from the
fruits so let's uh go and see what
Palm the palm tree looks like palm oil
palm oil
tree okay let me put that on the
screen if it yeah there we have it so
that's what the palm tree or palm plant
looks like this is the fruit it produces
it's a very uh it's got a very nice
Aroma and uh it's it's uh very rich in
oil
so that's what the fruit is like and
there is so this is from what you
generally extract palm oil now the
question is uh the question is how
healthy or not is palm oil and I am not
exactly an expert so let us go to
uh let's let's uh search for palm oil
dangers and we'll just review maybe an
article a research article search paper
and uh let's go
to let's go to this one
here so what's it
say uh so the dominance of see palm oil
is used in in processed foods now when
it comes to low income Nations you
typically will not see much prevalence
of processed or hyper processed foods
but when a nation is transitioning from
a low income status to a middle income
station status you're going to see an
increasing prevalence of hyper processed
foods like you know the packets of chips
and junk food and fast food and all that
and these typically use palm oil in
India for example is one of the major
importers I believe of palm oil now
uh okay so palm oil is one of the
world's most commonly used vegetable
oils it's used in s snacks and cosmetics
it's present in about half of frequently
used food and consumer product products
and so on and so forth so a meta
analysis of increased P palm oil
consumption in 3 23 countries found a
significant relationship with higher
mortality from ischemic heart disease
which is coronary heart disease another
systematic review found the P palmoil
consumption increased blood levels of
atherogenic low density lipoprotein
cholesterol uh and the wh has described
that the evidence linking saturated fat
consumption increased RIS risk of
cardiovascular disease is
convincing and there's a there's a lot
more over here so clearly it is
something that is hazardous okay palm
oil is not your not the kind of oil you
want to consume and it is also said that
uh they also said that coconut oil isn't
that healthy but we have been in India
using coconut oil for thousands of years
and we don't really I'm not sure if any
Studies have been done studying the
correlation between coconut oil
consumption and uh any health issues I
am not aware of any but palm oil
definitely is a risk factor so I would
say that palm oil
is hazardous to health it can it it is
co connected with an increased uh uh
prevalence of coronary heart disease and
uh bad cholesterol an increase in the
bad cholesterol in your blood so it
should be avoided what what that means
is that avoid eating hyper processed
foods all those fried things that come
in packages in
packets uh whether it is chips or
whatever curly fries or whatever it is
all that and other things as well maybe
canned products maybe maybe maybe what
do you call it quick noodles two minute
noodles or whatever it is all that stuff
you should read the ingredients and
sometimes it may not even be listed so
ideally what you want to do is just eat
natur natur foods which you cook them
which you cook yourself nothing
processed so that's the deal about palm
oil that's what I can say can it act as
a fuel in manufacturing or for
industrial purposes I'm sure you can use
it for that I'm sure it can be used so
the thing is India is a major importer
of palm oil I think India Imports
significant quantities of palm oil from
Malaysia as well as Indonesia and
recently there was some diplomatic St
spth between India and Malaysia and we
stopped importing it from Malaysia and
that was not good for Malaysia and they
kind of tried to convince India to start
importing again again from them so India
is a major importer of palm oil which
means a significant amount of the hyper
processed foods that we find in India
will have palm oil in there in them and
that is not good for your health so I
would say limit your consumption of all
this junk food fast food hyper processed
food eat healthy eat clean eat food that
is natural the best policy in life I
would say is to eat whatever your
ancestors were eating a thousand years
ago if they were eating it then you can
eat it
today and yeah so that's what I would
say that's a great juristic for what is
healthy and what's
not okay next question is by
SRI Shri rag ner
okay will you talk about photonic
integrated circuits this is an emerging
technology and the opportunities are
immense photonic integrated circuits
okay so what are photonic
circuits photonic circuits are circuits
that use light okay so we can we know
about computer chips microchips CPUs all
that these are these are microprocessors
and and various logic gates and all that
that are etched on Silicon Wafers
and it works through electrical impulses
right you have semiconductors that open
and close Gates and all that so that's
what you typically have in Computing
that's the kind of circuits you have on
Silicon Wafers photonic circuits or
photonic integrated circuits like Shri n
is saying these are devices that use
light these devices use
photons instead of electrons so instead
of using electrical signals you using
light impulses light signals photons to
perform the same functions various
functions like data transmission signal
processing uh computation all that so
that's what a photonic circuit is so it
is the same thing it is the analog of
electronic integrated circuits but they
operate using light that's what it is so
that's what it is now how do they work
the what are the building blocks the
what are the fundamental building blocks
of photonic circuits when it comes to
electric electronic circuits you have
silicon and you have semiconductor
semiconducting material that acts the
logic gates and you have electricity
that passes through this and it performs
various operations logic operations
logic gates and or or not exor and so on
so forth the same thing can be done
through photonic circuits now what are
the building blocks you will have first
of all wave guides wave guides are like
you can think of them as pipes through
which light passes so they they confine
light and the guide light to specific
paths similar to how wires guide
electric signals electrical signals so
that's wave guides they're typically
made from materials with high
refractive indexes know you know there
something in Optics called the
refractive index so you use wave guides
wave guides use are made from materials
with high refractive indexes such as
silicon or whatever else then you have
Splitters or couplers so these devices
will split or combine light signals from
different from different wave guides you
take multiple wave guides and you bring
them together the signals so this is
used for Distributing light signals
across various Paths of the circuits
then you have modulators you have
detectors you have resonators and lasers
and so on so all of this is what what
goes into creating a photonic integrated
circuit there are certain advantages
that photonic circuits have first of all
they are faster than your standard
Electrical uh circuits because light
travels faster than electrical signals
so photonic circuits photonic integrated
circuits will operate at higher speeds
so they are better they're actually
ideal for highspeed data transmission
processing and we already know that we
have fiber optics which make use of the
same thing and fiber optics have
excellent Fidelity and all that uh now
bandwidth when it comes to bandwidth
photonic circuits can handle a much
higher range of frequencies or
wavelengths compared to electronic
circuits so you will have much more data
that goes through your circuit the the
data throughput is much better than when
it comes to
electrical circuits there there is
heating when it comes to photonic
circuits these circuits they generated
they generate much less heat compared to
electronic circuits and so on when it
comes to electric circuits there is
there is a lot of the possibility of
electronic interference when you have
photonic circuits there are immune to
electromagnetic in uh interference for
example you need Faraday cages and all
that uh in the case of photon circuits
you won't have that and so on and there
are lots of applications of photonic
circuits for example telecommunications
you can use them in data centers you can
use them for computing itself Quantum
Computing is a great a very major
application of photonic circuits and all
that so that's what you have it that's
what you have now there are challenges
this is a new technology how to
integrate photonex circuits with
existing uh computational Systems
computer systems electronic systems how
do you do that that's challenging so you
to take a photonic signal a light signal
and convert it into an electric signal
when you are interfacing a photonic
based device with an electronic device
manufacturing is difficult there is a
lot of complexity and you need a lot of
precision these are all engineering
challenges which will eventually be
overcome that's where we are and then
there will be limitations of various
materials it depends on the kind of
materials you're using and how good
those materials are so finding materials
that are efficient as well as compatible
with existing semiconductor
manufacturing processes is a challenge
and so on so forth so it's an emerging
technology and it's going to eventually
become a big deal and we are already
transitioning towards that especially
when it comes to things like Quantum
Computing Etc so that is what photonic
integrated circuits are it is something
that can work actually better than the
electronic microprocessors and
electronic circuits that we have in use
today in all our devices whether it is a
phone a laptop or whatever it is
something that will eventually be a much
better much more robust much more
powerful technology there'll be very
less heating it'll be much faster so it
makes sense to to to invest in the
development of this technology and like
you say the opportunities are
imense okay rtic Power says if AI
becomes conscious and takes over power
do humans have any chance of regaining
control through military action what if
the AI takes over power only in the US
and not other parts of the world will be
fun will be fun okay let's say AI
becomes conscious and like you say I
think it takes overpower it takes
control
of it it comes to power somehow so what
does it mean when we say that I has
first of all conscious okay let's say it
becomes conscious the moment of the
singularity let's say it becomes
conscious and it takes power which means
that the government is no longer in
power it it takes power that's what you
mean essentially because in any country
let's say the US who is in power it's
the government that's in power what do
you mean by power what do you mean by
being in power it means you control
everything you control the financial
system you control the military you
control the police force you control the
administrative Machinery you control
Congress you control the lower house the
House of
Representatives you control
everything okay so it's a command and
control structure you give orders and
people execute those orders so
everything electricity power generation
all of that now how does AI take control
of the police force how does it do that
can it really do that it can't in
today's world it can't how does AI take
control of the military you have the
entire mil
hundreds of thousands of soldiers
Marines and Air Force and navy and the
Infantry and whatnot and the vehicles
that drive the planes they fly the ships
and boats and submarines they operate
how does AI take over that in today's
world it
can't if for AI to take control of
everything and to really take
power it needs to be able to control
every aspect of whatever we just spoke
about every aspect of the policing
process in a
country okay the command and control
structure of the police of every state
every uh County every city every town
every village the entire military
structure has to be controlled by the AI
so essentially this will only happen my
friends when the police force is
entirely robotic and the military is
entirely robotic as long as humans
perform the major tasks and roles AI
can't take over
understand that yeah can't take over
unless everything is fully
robotic and can be controlled by AI
itself remotely so so right now ai is
not in a position it may perhaps take
over the stock markets possibly it may
take over
telecommunications which means the
president can no longer give orders to
the Armed Forces do whatever and so on
there may be a disruption of
telecommunication that's what a can do
today if it takes over if it's malicious
uh it could possibly perhaps launch
nukes but I don't think that works
because the president's orders are
involved and there's a whole sequence of
events that needs to happen for the
president to to be able to give his
Ascent to press the big red button so
there is a human element involved in
this for sure and the AI won't be able
to override that at this point in
time so AI can take over an entire
country only when everything is entirely
automated everything is electronic and
everything is robotic which means all
your soldiers all your fighter planes
all your drones all your ships all your
submarines everything needs to be
robotic and all your police also have to
be robotic robotic police robotic police
dogs robotic everything only then can AI
really take control right now we're not
there yet okay but let's say
hypothetically 20 is down the line
everything is robotic and AI takes
control then can you take military
action well in that situation your
military is robotic and it's under the
control of the a so how do you take
military action right but let's say
today AI tries to Take Over Control it
takes over the stock market let's say it
takes over the electrical grade the
control of the electrical grid it takes
over telecommunications it it takes over
the control of the internet and all you
can still override that manually by
sending
engineers and whatever else and humans
to to physically cut off the AI or
whatever as long as AI doesn't have
control of any offensive weapons or
capabilities AI is
essentially helpless so right now we are
not there that not not yet that not yet
there so in the future so that's how an
can take over so that tells us what we
should not do what what steps and
measures we can take right now so that
AI can never take over which means don't
make the entire military robotic don't
make the entire police force robotic not
even a small percentage should be
robotic okay you can have autonomous
drones autonomous submarines to an
extent maybe the Americans want to have
and the Chinese want to have these
robotic dogs with machine guns attached
to them what you do too much of that
then a can take over yeah so so that's
what needs to happen it won't be fun
it'll be a disaster actually it'll be a
disaster Beyond imagination if AI takes
over robotic military and robotic police
force it is going to be disastrous
that's the Terminator Terminator
scenario that is exactly the Terminator
scenario and of course in The Terminator
scenario AI has control of the nukes and
it create it causes a World War by
launching nukes at the USSR or or Russia
so yeah you don't want to give AI
decision-making capabilities and nuclear
launch capabilities and you don't want a
robotic military and a robotic police
force you take these precautions AI
can't take over Beyond maybe the stock
market or whatever and you can always
override that unless the AI is
decentralized and you don't in which
case there are other complications but
yeah overall that
right okay Shivam Kumar says what is
space what is
space a good question once again it's
it's like the question what is fire what
is space so there are different ways of
looking at what space is the simplest
answer is that space is
the area
or it's that part of the universe that
lies between Interstellar objects like
star star system solar systems between
planets and so on it's the void between
astrophysical objects that is space and
as we know it is mostly a vacuum it's a
near it's a near vacuum not entirely a
vacuum because you have photons light
photons in in the void of interstellar
space you have that you also have a very
thin
diffuse you have some you have protons
you have
electrons you have hydrogen ions
essentially which which kind of
permeate Interstellar the interstellar
void or space at a very very very low
density which is why Interstellar space
is a near perfect vacuum almost perfect
uh it has gravitational fields space
okay the the large scale structure of
the universe is is mediated it is it is
governed it is it is yeah it is governed
by the U by the gravitational fields at
the very largest scales so you have
gravitational fields and then you have
dark matter most likely and you have
dark energy all of this is within space
and then space yeah so when we speak
about Dark Energy space is something
that is
expanding it's expanding and maybe so
dark energy is possibly something some
phenomenon some some some fluid some
Force whatever it is that is responsible
for the expansion the accelerating
expansion of space and not the space
space time so from the general
relativity perspective space is part of
a four-dimensional fabric called space
time space itself has three
dimensions that's dimensionality of
space uh Dr subash kak has a theory new
Theory very good theory in which space
could be e dimensional e is um look
check it out what is e the number e it
could be e dimensional Which is less
than three which is very very
interesting very very it's a fractal
number uh from the perspective of
quantum field Theory space is not empty
it is teaming with Quantum
fields and uh particle antiparticle
pairs are constantly popping into
existence and annihilating themselves
spontaneously so it is teeming with this
this Quantum Quantum fluctuations so all
of that is space space has a temperature
space is a wash in the whatever is left
of the after glow of the Big Bang which
we call the cosmic microwave background
radiation so so space is aash in that
and the temperature of space is aboutus
Celsius which is just about roughly
maybe- 271 so just a little bit above
absolute
zero and the temperature of space is the
temperature of the cosmic microwave
background radiation which is a very
very red shifted light the first light
that was that was formed in the universe
the which we could call the Afterglow of
the Big Bang so all of this is space
space you can you can Define it in so
many different
ways but the simplest definition from a
non physicist's perspective from a
completely lay person perspective is
that space is the void between
astrophysical objects you are at one
astrophysical object let's say you are
at a star or a planet and you want to go
to another planet or another star system
what comes in between this void that is
space all right all
right okay Malik Sayad says we know that
light requires about 8 minutes and 20
seconds to come to the earth from the
sun yes that's
yeah
300,000 kilom per second meters per
second yeah uh what is the speed of
light how can I forget is it 300,000
kilometers per second or is it meters
per second let's let's let's
quickly
um let's check it out let's go to speed
of light I think yeah speed of light
right yeah meters per second about
300,000 m/ second is the speed of light
so once again the question is we know
that light takes this much time about 8
minutes 20 seconds to travel from the
Sun to the Earth now what does it mean
if the sun hypothetically
disappears then we will not see the sun
after 8 minutes or 20 seconds my
question is will the earth continue
orbiting the Sun for the until that 8
minutes and 20 seconds is elapsed or
will the impact of The Disappearance of
the Sun be instantaneous if it's
instantaneous then we can say there is
nothing faster than the light so can we
use it for human travel in future okay
good question okay so let's let's put
the solar system on the screen let us
put that on the screen okay uh one one
second let me yeah let's go this and
solar system
and uh so this is what the solar system
looks like let's take this as an example
so we have the
sun okay this is this is a
very let's
say let's take this toy image is an
example so you have the Sun at the
center then you have the planets around
it Mercury Venus Earth Mars Jupiter
Saturn Uranus Neptune and they have
omitted Pluto but whatever okay so we
have these objects in orbit around the
sun now let us do a thought experiment
it's called a thought experiment or
aanin experiment let's say we make the
sun disappear like that so all of a
sudden there is no Sun at the center of
the solar system what happens now what
happens so there are two perspectives
two ways of look looking at this so keep
this image of the solar system in your
in your
mind the sun with the planets going
around it it's a very rough image but
you get it
so so we make the sun magically
disappear in our thought experiment so
when the sun disappears what happens
there are two perspectives like I said
one is the Newtonian perspective one is
the einsteinian or general relativistic
perspective from the Newtonian
perspective gravity is an action at a
distance
Force okay so from the neonian
perspective the moment the sun
disappears all the planets that are
going in circle suddenly will be in free
fall they'll just fly off in all
directions
instantaneously instantaneously they'll
all fly off because of the sun's
gravitational pull they are being forced
to travel in circles or ellipses okay so
let's say circular paths just to make it
simple they're traveling in circles
because they being pulled by the
gravitational force of the sun if the
sun disappears they will instantly fly
off in straight
lines okay that's what happens from the
neonian
perspective now okay and and that's what
happens from the ne perspective now what
about the general relativistic
perspective from the perspective of
general
relativity gravity is not an action at a
distance Magical Force what we perceive
as the force of gravity is actually the
curvature of SpaceTime which is produced
by the presence of
mass so in GR in general
relativity the universe is a
four-dimensional stage space time space
and time together four-dimensional
structure and the presence of mass
curves SpaceTime and the curvature of
SpaceTime tells Mass how to move so
because this sun this massive object is
present over there that's why the space
type is curved by it and this curvature
of the SpaceTime tells all the planets
to move in circular or elliptical
orbits now in general relativity there's
a speed limit which is the speed of
light nothing travels faster than the
speed of light so if the sun magically
disappears
then the ABS so it's its light rays are
traveling to the earth now it suddenly
disappears so there's no more light
coming in but those light rays which
were already emitted they will keep on
traveling towards the Earth and for the
next 8 minutes and 20 seconds we will
keep on seeing the sun even though it's
actually disappeared already so we will
not come to know for 8 minutes and 20
seconds that the sun has actually
disappeared and it's only then that the
gravitational effects will become
apparent so so for 8 minutes 20 seconds
the Earth will continue in its orbit and
it will continue seeing sunlight and
seeing the Sun as if it's there it's
only after 8 minutes 20 seconds that you
will suddenly perceive darkness that the
sun has disappeared and then Earth and
the other planets will fly off in
different directions that's what
actually happens so the correct
perspective is the einsteinian or
general relativistic perspective the
Newtonian perspective is the older and
rather obsolete perspective we still use
Newtonian physics a lot when it comes to
let's say space travel uh if you want to
send people to the moon and bring it
bring them bring it back bring it bring
them back you can use Newtonian
Mechanics for it you don't need to use
general relativity that's how accurate
Newtonian mechanics actually is but the
correct picture the correct perspective
is the general relativistic perspective
so what will really happen is what I
just described even though the sun is
actually disappeared by Magic we won't
know it for eight 8 minutes and 20
seconds it's only then that we will
suddenly realize the sun has disappeared
so that's how it goes and we can't use
these magical effects for travel faster
than light or any such thing because you
cannot break the speed limit you can't
violate the universal speed limit which
is C the speed of light all
right okay isue says have you watched
Netflix three body problem is this a
real phenomenon so I have read the book
a long time ago when it first came out
the first book The Three body problem by
chikin Leu a Chinese science fiction
writer great book very very good book
and uh recently a Netflix thing came out
documentary not documentary of Series
right I think I saw a couple of episodes
of that and
uh so what is the three body problem is
the question is it a real phenomenon so
the three body problem is a bound State
problem it's a Newtonian bound State
problem so bound State problem s can be
solved in a variety of ways you can use
if it's the Earth Moon system for
example or the Earth Sun System you can
just use neonian
mechanics to calculate the orbit and all
that calculate the size of the orbit the
periodicity of the orbit and so on so
forth we have Kepler's laws which are
part of Newtonian mechanics Celestial
Dynamics and so on you can compute
orbits and trajectories and whatnot
using the Newtonian uh using new in
physics you can also actually solve the
shinger equation for the Earth's sun
system or the Earth Earth Moon
system using a gravitational potential
okay that is complicated I'll not go
into that sounds complicated you don't
know what a grav gravitational potential
is and so on but you can actually you
solve this bound State problem not using
NE neutronian mechanics but using the
quantum formulation the Stringer
equation that also works
but it's a bound State problem Earth Sun
or Earth Moon now instead of a two body
problem Earth Sun let's say we solve we
try to solve a three body problem
somewhere in space there are three
gravitating
objects they are close to each other
which means they feel the pull of each
other's gravity so it's not a bound
state of two objects two gravitating
objects it's a bounce of three
gravitating objects that's the three
body problem now that is something that
typically doesn't have a stable solution
there are a few stable Solutions but
most solutions are unstable Solutions
which means that the bound State the
bound state is unstable it breaks up it
will evolve for a time and then it will
break up it is
unstable so it is a bounce so it's not a
bounce State actually now there are a
bunch of solutions that and and it's
very difficult it's a very chaotic
system it's very hard to to did to find
Solutions uh from the Newtonian
perspective now if you want to see what
some solutions look like I could do that
um
okay so this is an image that represents
a few stable solutions to the three body
problem as you can see each of these of
these uh images represents a three-body
system
and it has stable Solutions which means
that the bound State remains stable it
doesn't break up what does it mean by
for a bound state to break up it means
that one one or more of these objects
will fly off into space and not return
together not come back into the into the
system so these systems that you seeing
these Solutions are stable Solutions and
they can persist
indefinitely and recently I believe uh
some some some physicists or
mathematicians derived a whole whole
bunch of more solutions maybe 12,000 or
so solutions to this three body problem
so
overall it's a it's a chaotic and
unstable system and that's the premise
behind this this uh the science fiction
book and the series The Three body
problem so yes is it a real phenomenon
yeah you take three bodies three objects
gravitating objects of reasonably
similar masses you're going to have a
chaotic system which typically will
break up over time
so it's a real phenomenon but the the
what what whatever else is depicted in
the story in the science fiction story
where the the unfold of photon and all
that that is in the realm of Science
Fiction for sure okay so we don't know
we don't know if a proton can be
unfolded the premise is that there are
lots of hidden Dimensions multiple
Dimensions String Theory premise maybe
maybe 10 Dimensions maybe 11 maybe 26
dimensions and maybe this alien um
civilization has has the technology to
unfold the dimensions and engineer the
inside of a of a proton so that sort of
thing and then there is some stretching
of of quantum mechanics in there when
they when they say that you can uh you
can have a quantum entanglement in which
there is transmission of information
that is not right so that it's not how
it works some of it is is fiction some
of it is actual
science okay okay next
question okay Rohan bidi says is it true
that achieving absolute zero temperature
is impossible and is there an upper
limit on how on how hot an object can
get so what is the upper limit of
temperature is a question
right so first of all the lowest
temperature you can have is called
absolute zero absolute zero is aboutus 2
73°
C which is 0 Kelvin H so absolute 0o is
0 Kelvin on the Kelvin scale which is
minus 273 something degrees Celsius and
Fahrenheit it's something else so that
is what absolute zero is and that is the
theoretical lowest temperature that you
can have so theoretically the lowest
temperature can be minus 273 something
Celsius which is which is 0 Kelvin it's
not 0 deges Kelvin it's 0 Kelvin so at
this temperature absolute zero the
motion of all particles in a substance
will seize which means that the
substance substance will have zero
kinetic energy of course there is
something called Zero Point Energy which
I will not go into it's a quantum
mechanical thing but overall all energy
all all motion of molecules vibration
whatever rotations Etc everything will
seize so the substance will have zero
kinetic energy now is this possible in
in reality in
reality the it is is not possible to
achieve absolute zero and this is
because of the third law of
thermodynamics which states that the
temperature as the temperature of a
system approaches absolute zero its
entropy or the the measure of the
disorder on the system will approach a
minimum value okay and this law also
implies that it's impossible to reach
absolute zero in a finite number of
steps so you can reach absolute zero but
it will take you an infinite number of
steps to get there so that's why it's
it's practically not possible so in
practice if you have a system let's say
you have a box and you're refrigerating
it you're taking as much heat out as
possible so the system Inside the Box
gets colder and colder okay now as the
system gets colder it's going to get
more and more difficult it's going to
get increasingly difficult to remove
whatever heat is left because there's
already very little heat left and you're
going to have to do tremendous amount of
work work to extract that heat out and
take it out okay so there are various
methods that are used for cooling uh
Refrigeration has your standard methods
then there is laser Cooling and and and
whatnot so these methods can bring your
substance or your thing whatever it is
your gas or liquid or whatever it is to
very close to absolute zero but you can
never reach exactly absolute zero
because of these limitations
thermodynamic constraints quantum
mechanical limitations and all that so
achieving absolute zero is practically
impossible it's not going to happen you
will not be able to achieve absolute
zero now what's the upper limit on
temperature is there an upper limit on
how hot an object can get well
theoretically unlike absolute zero there
is no known upper limit no there's no
known fundamental upper limit to
temperature so you can get you can make
something as hot as you possibly can
using practical means so there is no
fundamental upper theoretical limit on
temperature uh there is something called
a plank temperature okay so the plank
temperature is uh approximately what 10
rais to 32
Kelvin 10 rais to and and when it comes
to the highest temperatures we have
achieved on on Earth I think when it
comes to colliding like the large hydron
collider or whatever you may have a
temperature of maybe on the of the order
of a billion Kelvin 10 ra to 9 Kelvin
but the plank temperature is roughly
about 10 to 32 Kelvin so that
is a difference of a factor of 10 to 23
which is ridiculous enormous so the
plank temperature is so that is derived
from various fundamental physical
constants it it represents the scale the
plank temperature represents the scale
at which the effects of quantum gravity
are expected to become significant uh
and uh at the plank temperature or above
the plank temperature the current
physical theories will break down I mean
the we don't have uh we believe it is
the current physical theories like
general relativity quantum mechanics or
whatever else they are insufficient to
describe the behavior of matter and
energy at the plank temperature or above
the plank temperature so we don't know
how matter energy Etc will behave at
that scale and above that scale so it's
not it's not a limit but it's it's where
our understanding of of physics breaks
down okay so that's what it is so there
is no established theoretical
fundamental upper limit on the
temperature that you can achieve but the
plank temperature is is a theoretical
boundary Beyond which our understanding
of physics breaks down it no longer
applies so that's what what it is so
absolute zero achieving absolute zero is
impossible from a practical perspective
achieving as hot a temperature as you
can is not
impossible theoretically or or
practically but or understanding of
physics breaks down at and Beyond the
plank temperature and obviously when it
comes to a practical perspective the
highest temperature we can achieve is of
the order of 10 of of a of of a billion
Kelvin 10 rais to 9 Kelvin which is way
way way way way below the plank
temperature it's pun compared to the
plank temperature so yeah that's the
answer okay feminist
Slayer says are electromagnetic waves
attached to space and if so does it mean
that they don't have their own speed but
rather travel with a speed of space
which would be the Hubble speed in the
present time well okay inter in question
the Hubble speed is what 60 something or
70 something uh units
right uh now that's not the speed of
light we know that light travels at
300,000 m/s that's that's the speed of
light roughly roughly okay don't don't
nitpick don't be pedantic it's roughly
300,000 meters per spe per second that's
the speed of light in vacuum and also in
air mostly almost the same in water and
other substances in in other media the
speed of light is is less than that of
the speed of light in vacuum and air but
you get
it so the question the real question
you're asking is are these
electromagnetic waves attached to space
which actually what you're actually
asking
is what are you asking what you're
asking is do they need a medium to
propagate is space the medium in which
the propagate it is it is but here's the
answer electromagnetic waves don't need
a
medium in which to propagate so space is
you can you can think of it as a
vacuum and they travel through space
they're not attached to space and it's
not the expansion of SpaceTime that is
making electromagnetic waves travel okay
it's not that they
travel within space they travel through
space they're not attached to space or
space time so they can travel they don't
need a vacuum to travel so they can
travel through space they can travel
through air the atmosphere of the earth
they can travel through the atmosphere
of Venus they can travel through water
but in water it doesn't work work they
don't travel they don't propagate that
well which is why if you go below a
certain depth under the oceans it's
complete darkness because they can no
longer reach there so each medium is
different and so on so so yeah that's
the answer the electromagnetic waves are
they have their own their own speed
which is the speed of light that's the
fundamental Cosmic speed limit and
electromagnetic wave is made up of an
electrical component and a magnetic
component that oscillate at at right
angles at 90 degrees with each other and
that's how they propagate so they're not
attached to space they don't need a
medium for being able to travel and they
travel at different speeds in different
media depending on the properties of the
medium all
right Arjun sin says what are what is
what are cosmic red shifts what is a red
shift if you heard of the Doppler effect
so red shift is about the application of
the Doppler effect to
light so now let us uh go to
let's let's let me put an illustration
of the Doppler effect on the screen and
then let me explain what red shift
is so
Doppler
effect so here we have the Doppler
effect with a Sound
Source okay let's say you have two cars
let's say you have a start okay with a
train right we we are all familiar with
the doler effect with with a train
so when you have a train coming towards
you at a high speed and the train blares
its horn or siren you're going to hear a
very high pitched sound as it's coming
towards you but the moment the brain
passes you you're standing on the
platform and the trade is coming towards
you it's going to be very high pitched
sound the moment it passes you and it
starts going away from you the sound
changes in frequency and it becomes a
lower pitched sound that is the Doppler
effect and the reason for that is
because when the the train is coming
towards you the sound waves are are
compressed that's why they sound higher
pitched or the sound as if they have a
higher frequency because they do have a
higher frequency from your perspective
and when the train passes you and it
goes away from you then then the the
source of the sound is moving away and
that's why the sound waves are stretched
out and they appear to have a lower
frequency uh so that's how the Doppler
effect works with respect to sound and
the same thing happens with light
so when a light source so light is an
electromagnetic wave this wave is going
to have a frequency or wavelength and
when a light source is moving towards
you those light waves are going to get
compressed squashed and and they're
going to have a higher frequency and a
shorter wavelength which means they will
the light will be shifted towards the
blue end of the spectrum you know Vib
gor right violet indigo blue yellow
orange red the
seven uh elements of the of the spectrum
so when light is is when the light
source is moving towards you the light
is going to be shifted towards blue end
of the spectrum that's called Blue shift
and when a light source is moving away
from you then the light waves are going
to get stretched out and the light is
going to be shifted towards the red end
of the spectrum and that is red shift
so when you observe red shift in the
cosmos When You observe and how do you
know that something is red shifted so
there are certain
characteristic uh lines in the
Spectrum character in spectroscopy you
know that you know that when you that
each element has certain transitions
which produce characteristic lines in
the
Spectrum want to want want to see what a
spectrum looks like okay let's let's
look at the spectr
graph Spectrum let's see what a spectrum
looks like spectral
lines so these are spectral lines okay
every
gas you have you have a star in which
you have different elements you have
hydrogen helium there's going to be
other elements also so they're going to
have various uh lines in the Spectrum
and we can we can break down these lines
into the element into the components
using something called a spectrometer or
spectrograph so you here you have
various yeah spectral lines and all that
so now we know that each spectral line
has at which frequency it
exists so for example if you have if you
burn sodium it produces a very
characteristic line on the
Spectrum and we know what is the
frequency of that but when you observe
that line in the spectrum of light
that's coming from a Galaxy you're going
to see that it's not at that frequency
it's at a different frequency if it is
shifted towards the red end of the
spectrum then that Galaxy is red shifted
if it is shifted towards the blue end of
the spectrum it is blue shifted so when
you find that light is red shifted it
means the Galaxy is moving away from you
and depending on how much it is red
shifted you can determine how fast it is
moving away from you and similarly for
blue shift so that is what a red shift
is that's what the blue blue shift is
how do we know galaxies are
rotating because if you see the light
coming from one end of the Galaxy is
going to be either red shifted or blue
shifted in the other end if this part is
red shifted this part will be blue
shifted and if this is red shifted this
will be blue shifted so you know that
one end is moving away from you and one
end is moving towards you that's how we
know that galaxies rotate and then yeah
that's how it goes so that is what
Cosmic red shift is what that is what
red shift overall
is Rohan says why is gravity the weakest
of the four fundamental forces of nature
so we know of four we know of four
fundamental
forces the four that we know of the weak
electromagnetic force the strong
sorry the weak nuclear force the strong
nuclear force the electromagnetic force
and the gra and and gravity these are
the four forces that we are aware of
okay so now how do we know what are the
strengths of these forces that's a good
question and let me uh once again go to
our friend Google and there's a great
website that you can check out okay if
you want to see basic physics hyper
hyper per
physics so hyper physics is a great
website and let's look at coupling
constants
constants coupling constants for the
fundamental forces and we go there okay
let me IG this
bigy okay so
uh so every Force has a coupling
constant I'll not go into what a
coupling constant is because that will
be a whole different explanation but
every Force has a coupling
constant so the strong force has alpha s
the electronic electromagnetic force is
Alpha the weak Force as a coupling
constant and the and gravity has a
coupling constant and see the strengths
so the so the coupling constant strength
for the strong force is of the order of
one it's
dimensionless could actually be 0.1 or
something but let's say it's one then
the strength of the the coupling
constant the
value of the coupling constant of the
electromag magnetic force is 1 upon
137 so that's about of the order of 10
ra to minus
two the weak force that it's coupling
constant
has a value of 10us 6 so that's four
times weaker than the electromagnetic
force roughly and then gravity has a its
coupling constant has a value of 10us 39
which is
ridiculous it's about 10 ra to it's
about 10 ra to 33 times weaker than the
weak Force incredibly weak that's how
incredibly weak gravity is okay so
gravity is the weakest of forces by a by
a massive margin incredible margin the
weak force is the other weakest force uh
neutrinos interact only via the weak
interaction and the sun produces
trillions trillions of solar neutros per
second and right now trillions of solar
neutros are passing through my body
right now trillions of solar neutros are
passing through my body every second
and none of them is interacting with me
no interaction I don't even know that
this is happening I don't sense anything
but it's there so the weak force is so
weak that the enormous majority of these
neutros don't interact with with regular
matter you know electromagnetic
matter but the gravitational force is
about 10 ra to 33 time weaker than the
weak Force imagine how weak it is so
that gives you an illustration of the
relative strengths and weaknesses of the
forces and the gravitational force is
the weakest by far now why is it so
that's the question we don't
know there are theories there are
hypotheses as to why it is so but we
don't really know and one of the
straightforward answers I can give you
is that string theory gives you uh gives
you gives you an explanation of why it
is so but we have no proof of that
string theory M Theory brain brain world
theory whatever you want to call it so
in in M Theory
uh the
universe uh was born from the Collision
of what's called two brains a brain is a
three-dimensional object which lives
inside a higher dimensional
bulk so if you have a sheet of paper
it's kind of a two-dimensional object it
has length and breadth and no thickness
almost almost so a sheet of paper is a
two-dimensional object that resides in
in a threedimensional world correct
similarly the
universe it it is kind of you can say a
brain a three-dimensional object that
resides in a let's say 10 dimensional
bulk spring Theory bulk and the universe
was was formed the Big Bang was the
result of the Collision Of Two Brains
that's how it is in in in brain world
theory M the theory
so in string theory super String Theory
you may have 10 or 11 Dimensions now
where are these Dimensions why don't we
see them we can see length breadth and
height right every object has a certain
length certain breadth and certain
height and time can be the fourth
dimension so so we are aware of four
dimensions we can perceive and sense and
observe four dimensions but what are
these 10 Dimensions that Str the talks
about or 11 Dimensions or 26
dimensions are these Dimensions so
according to string theory these
dimensions are Ultra compactified they
are very small very tiny Dimensions you
can't see them but they exist so
according to string theory super String
Theory the three forces the strong force
the weak force and the electromagnetic
force they
are their effects are felt only in the
three dimensions that we
observe they propagate only in these
three dimensions but gravity propagates
in all Dimensions so much of of the
strength of gravity leaks out in these
unseen dimensions and that's why it is
so weak in the three dimensions that we
perceive that is the theory do we have
any evidence of that
none okay have we ever observed extra
Dimensions
no and if extra dimensions and all that
existed then we then the LHC would
probably the large hydron collider would
probably have produced micro black holes
okay so before this thing was turned on
the large Hydro collider in the 2000s
before
2010 there there were lots of papers
that were published that predicted that
the large hyon collider would
produce about one micro black hole per
second or something like that and that
had something to do with extra
dimensions and all that and it never
happened we know it never happened and
there was campaign a movement to stop
the LHC because it would produce
possibly micro black holes and these
black holes would eat the Earth up so we
would stop we would we would be
destroyed so there was this campaign
to to stop the the large hyon collider
anyway so the only theory that kind of
explains why gravity is so weak is super
String Theory but there is no
evidence that proves the correctness or
validity of string theory but it makes
sense from that perspective so that's
perhaps why gravity is the weakest of
the
forces uh let's take a couple more
questions what was there before the Big
Bang why did the Big Bang occur at the
exact time it happened so we don't know
we have no data from the from before the
Big Bang whatever data we have whatever
observational evidence we have see
whatever theories you make have to be in
synchronicity with the observational
data empirical evidence and the laws of
physics so we know the laws of physics
at the largest scales the universe is
governed by general relativity we know
that and then we have all this data of
all this observational evidence of stars
galaxies the red shifted galaxies
they're all moving away from each from
us and the the the expansion of the
universe is is getting is accelerating
we have Cosmic microwave background
radiation all of this data all of this
evidence is there so that is what helped
us
formulate what is called Big Bang
cosmology the Lambda CDM Lambda cold
Dark Matter model of the universe okay
but this data that we have it says
nothing whatsoever of what could have
existed before the birth of the universe
the birth the big bag so from a data
perspective from a scientific
perspective we have zero evidence of
anything that came before the Big Bang
so we don't know what was before the Big
B but there are theories like like I
said in in M Theory in super String
Theory
Etc uh the Big Bang itself was the was
the result of the collision between two
brains three threedimensional brains
that exist in a higher dimensional bulk
and the Collision of these two brains
and the energy it impa it it released or
the energy of the Collision was what
created the big bang and the Big Bang is
the creation of the universe so maybe
it's that but we have zero evidence for
that mathematically it makes sense and
all that but evidence is key in science
a theory if it is not falsifiable is not
a scientific theory it's philosophy or
religion so from that perspective string
theory is all philosophy it's not
science
well
okay uh MOS says we know energy is
created from Mass no we don't know that
we don't know that okay uh we don't know
that energy is created from Mass now can
this reaction be reversed I read it I
read it can be but require
enormous amounts of energy like big bang
to
happen so can Mass be converted into
energy can energy be converted into mass
that sort of thing so can Mass be
converted into energy is essentially
what he is asking yes it
can Mass can be converted into Pure
Energy I'll tell you how let's say you
have a proton let's let's say you have a
hydrogen atom what's a hydrogen atom
it's a proton as in the nucleus
and it has an electron that goes around
kind of goes around the proton so that's
what a hydrogen atom is an electron in
orbit in a shell orbit around a proton
which is the nucleus so that is let's
say the matter the mass that you have
one hydrogen atom now how do you convert
it into Pure Energy very simple you
bring in an atom of anti-hydrogen which
has a which has an anti at the center
and a positron in a shell orbit around
the POS the the antiproton so that's
hydrogen one atom of hydrogen one atom
of anti-hydrogen that's matter
antimatter you bring them them together
they're going to give off they they're
going to annihilate and give off Pure
Energy generally in the form of
photons yeah so it can happen so matter
can be converted into pure energy by
annihilating it with anti matter
right okay ad Guru Prasad he asks a very
interesting question and the question is
about entropy please explain
entropy entropy I've had so many
discussions and arguments about entropy
in the past
anyway what is entropy entropy is a
fundamental Concept in physics but also
in chemistry okay and it essenti
actually is related to the degree of
disorder or the degree of Randomness in
a physical system what's a physical
system let's say you have gas in a box
that's a physical system how much
disorder how much Randomness do you have
in this gas in the box that's that
measure that measure of disorder or
Randomness is called entropy so entropy
it plays a crucial critical role in the
second law of Thermodynamics and it is
important
applications implications in various
processes chemical reactions and so on
so forth so in physics we have a field a
branch of physics called
thermodynamics in which entropy is a
measure of the number of see you have a
system you have a gas in a box what is
the number of specific ways in which
your gas this thermodynamic system can
be
arranged without changing the overall
state of the system so this is the
measure of the randomness of the of the
system the measure of disorder of the
system so the ways in which you can
arrange a cooled gas it's different from
the number of ways in which you can
arrange a hotter gas and so on and so
forth ice versus water and so on so the
second law of Thermodynamics it says
that the total entropy of a of an
isolated system can never decrease over
time and this implies that natural
processes move from States of uh move
they tend to move they want to move
towards a state of Maximum entropy or
thermodynamic equilibrium and then you
bring in statistical mechanics and all
that you know you have the the boltzman
entropy formula s is equal to kbl Ln
Omega where KB is the Bol span constant
and Omega is the number of mic micr
States s is entropy and so and so on so
forth so entropy is is a
statistical property of a system it's
the measure of the disorder of a system
an intrinsic particle like a proton or a
neutron or a bound State can never have
entropy it's only a combination it's
only a bunch of particles a system made
of lots of particles that can have
entropy and there is entropy has it has
a meaning in chemistry as well entrop
when you have a chemical reaction in
chemistry the entropy of the system
changes and the kind the the the change
in entropy is is it it tells you it is
it tells you how spontaneously the
reaction happens so the spontaneity of a
reaction it is dependent on the kind of
entropy change the system under goes in
a chemical reaction and there's
something called the Gibs free energy
equation and that tells you how it
happens the positive or negative change
in entropy will determine the
spontaneity of the reaction and so on so
forth so entropy um it
is you you
can factor in molecular motion you can
factor in lots of other things but
overall it's the measure of the disorder
of a system in a system you have lots of
components typically gas molecules or or
you have water or you have a liquid so
you have molecules in
various various configurations and the
amount of disorder in a system that is
the measure of that is the entropy so
for example if you take the system the
human brain the human brain is a highly
highly ordered system so it's entropies
going to be incredibly low and probably
the lowest entropy system in the
universe may be the human brain because
it's so orderly so there's very little
disorder and so on so all of that is
entropy entropy is a statistical it's a
thermodynamic property it's a
statistical property of a system and
please remember that intrinsic particles
do not carry entropy they don't have
entropy okay we'll take one last
question before we go into the live chat
so geopolitical dub says uh what or who
makes the perception what makes the P
perception that scientists cannot be
dharmic or religious as he or she sees
everything scientifically in Dharma is
not science okay so let's be
clear there is a difference
between science and philosophy science
and spirituality science and religion
now religion and Dharma are different
the Indian system dhic system Sy is
different from the abrahamic systems
which are religions theic system is
different and so on but when it comes to
science versus let's say
philosophy philosophy and spirituality
can deal with non-physical objects when
we talk about the concept of the
soul the soul is not something you can
measure it's not something you can OB
obser observe soul is non observable
it's not measurable it doesn't have a
weight doesn't doesn't have mass it
doesn't occupy volume as far as we know
it's a non-physical object so when we
talk about non-physical objects that is
beyond the realm of science right when
you are a scientist you are absolutely
disciplined that you only deal with deal
with physical objects physical phenomena
and observable quantities that is
science and we when we talk about
philosophy and religion and Dharma when
we talk about the soul and we talk about
ethics and morality these are not
physical things so you cannot bring
science into that or you cannot take
that and and try to apply science to
that or and you cannot make science
subject to whatever laws may or may not
exist Rel related to these non-physical
objects that is that's the difference
disting that's what distinguishes that's
what differentiates science from
philosophy and religion now can a
scientist be
religious is it wrong for a scientist to
to be religious let me give you some
examples have there been scientists who
have been religious in
history have you heard of shinas
ramanujan one of the greatest
mathematicians in known
history mathematician well he was deeply
deeply profoundly religious he said that
every mathematical equation is is
something to do with God and he used to
see dreams of of his of his goddess his
family goddess and she used to give him
equations and used to wake up and write
those equations and they would
invariably be correct
so he was religious deeply religious
that's one
example uh George
Sudan ECG Sudan one of the greatest
theoretical physicists of the 20th
century he should have won three Nobel
prizes he was born into a Christian
family in Kerala or South India
somewhere the Southern India but he was
not a practicing Christian he was a
practicing Hindu and maybe that
contributed to him not winning a single
Nobel Prize he should have won three
Nobel prizes that's how great and that's
how brilliant George sashan was do you
know do you want to see what it looks
like let me put him on the screen one of
the greatest physicists that we can in
our
history
um let me put Google on the
screen so this is a scientist who was
religious okay one of the greats one of
the genuine greats he was religious he
believed in
God who else who else can we think of
scientists who believed in God ah George
lumetra who was George lumetra let me
tell you let's Wikipedia him as always
Wikipedia is not a reliable source of
information but just for the sake of
convenience we'll put Wikipedia on the
screen so this guy Jor Lum was a
theoretical physicist he he proposed The
Big Bang Theory that's how significant
he is he proposed The Big Bang Theory
and he also derived what is now called
Hubble's Law and so on and who was this
guy he was a Catholic priest and he was
a theoretical physicist okay let's let's
take a look at uh something about him
work blah blah blah etc etc what do we
have uh let's go to
this uh let's go this
arive paper about him editorial note to
the beginning of the world from the
point of view of quantum
theory so this is about a paper that uh
Lum wrote and what does he write here
let's see this is his this is something
he had crossed out he says I think that
everyone who believes in a Supreme Being
supporting every being and every acting
believes also that God is essentially
hidden and may be glad to see how
present physic provides a wheel hiding
the creation so this is a guy who's a
Catholic priest he believes in God and
he is the person who proposed The Big
Bang Theory one of the greatest
physicists okay theoretical physicist
and Men the predictions his predictions
were all born out they all came out to
be true Big Bang Theory Cosmic microwave
background Edition and much more and he
believed in God
so this is a Catholic guy or Catholic
priest similarly why can't you be a
dharmic person and and still be a
physicist or a scientist of course you
can George Sudan he was a dhic guy dhic
man one of the great Geniuses of the
20th century
so when you do physics when you do
science you do it through the scientific
method you don't bring in religion in
there otherwise you're going to end up
with nonsense the scientific method
emerged out of India now there are
people will say that you should okay I
not go into that unnecessary controversy
but that's a deal so you can be a
physicist while also being religious
because as a physicist especially if you
are at The Cutting Edge of physics at
the bleeding edge of physics between the
known and the unknown the possible and
the impossible that's typically
theoretical phys physics then you know
that more than 95% of the universe is
unknown to us so when there is such such
when there when there are such enormous
unknowns it makes sense to have a to to
consider seriously the possibility that
there could be a Divinity out there so I
would say most
physicists the more brilliant they are
the more agnostic they are and some of
them actually are believers in God so
there is so it's so some physicist some
scientists will say that it is wrong for
a scientist to believe in God I think
those people are idiots to put it very
crudely but
yeah okay I think we're done with the
with the questions from the comments now
let's take some questions from the live
chat now please ask me questions about
science and physics when it comes to
geopolitics and other things we'll take
that day after tomorrow not tomorrow so
in case you came in later if you came in
late I am supposed to have a live stream
tomorrow about geopolitics history and
current affairs I am postponing it
postponing it today after tomorrow
because I have to be in Delhi tomorrow
I'm attending the inauguration and
swearing in swearing in of Prime
Minister Modi so I cannot refuse that I
I've been invited very graciously so I
have accepted that so that live stream
will happen on Monday Monday 900 PM all
right so let's take some questions from
the live
chat no no questions about history
please you can ask me ask me those
questions in the history live stream
history
geopolitics Nishan says how do space
telescopes like the Hubble Space
Telescope the James web Space Telescope
create images are they accurate a
telescope usually have lens usually has
lenses and you have to understand Optics
so one so it's usually lenses and
mirrors or lenses or mirrors and you can
have prisms as well there are different
kinds of telescopes some are reflective
just like your cameras I don't know
where's my camera I've got a bunch of
cameras so you have something called an
SLR camera or a DSLR digital single lens
reflector so when you have a lens a
camera has a lens Right light comes to
the lens it's focused on on an element
which is a reflective element and that
it's a mirror which ref reflects the
light onto the the digital processor and
that's how the image is formed similarly
when it comes to Hubble or James web I
think when it comes to Hubble there's a
gigantic primary
lens and I don't remember what happens
inside is there a reflector is there a
prism is it another lens but there are
Optical elements in the case of the
James web Space Telescope okay let's
take a look at what it looks like let's
put that on the
screen jwst James web Space Telescope so
this is what it looks like uh so you can
see it's it's got a bunch it's a
compound
mirror and these are hexagonal mirrors
all put together and there is and that
light whichever it is whichever is
collected on the mirror is reflected
into this smaller element which will
then process that so let us say
schematic
schematic schematic diagram do we have
it so yeah if you if you look at this
it'll tell you what are the what are the
components and how it actually
works so you have the primary mirror 18
hexagonal segments made up of beril and
Co with gold there a secondary mirror
which which gathers the reflected light
and then it it gives that light to the
primary scientific equipments and these
equipments they all process the light
and give you the scientific data and so
on and so forth so that's how it works
so different telescopes work in
different
ways uh you have earth-based telescopes
you have space based telescopes like
Hubble then you have the infrared
telescope which is James web
so the James web Space Telescope so the
Hubble Space Telescope it primarily
gathers light and data in the visible V
visible part of the spectrum whatever we
see with our eyes is the visible range
of the spectrum and that's mostly the
the light spectrum in which Hubble
gathers light and and data a little bit
of infrared as well when it comes to
jwst James web Space Telescope it is
designed to operate in the infrared
range of the spectrum because because we
want to we want to uh be able to see the
oldest light in the
universe and the oldest light in the
universe comes from very very far away
which is why it is highly stretched out
it is red shifted and it is no longer
visible to our eyes it is so red shifted
so it is infrared light so that's why
the Hub of the James web telescope
operates in the infrared uh range of the
spectrum and that's why there we've had
to put it in orbit around the L2 lrange
point in the shadow of the
earth so that is very cool and it is not
it doesn't uh it is not impacted by
light from the sun and so on so forth so
yeah that's how it operates to
understand really how it operates you to
see the schematic diagram and understand
Optics and understand various effects
and uh that's how it's done and is it
accurate it's tremendously accurate of
course it is otherwise why would you
spend so much money sending this
instrument so far away and all that yeah
so it is indeed very much
accurate
okay okay Zeus says we have heard the
famous sentence either we are alone in
the universe or we are not both are
equally terrifying my question is what
if we are the alone the only
civilization in the universe well that's
terrifying it's which means that if we
mess up and we somehow extinguish
ourselves then there's no intelligent
life left in the
universe right I mean we are always in
the brink of disaster since the 20th
century when we
discovered radioactivity in nuclear
weapons when we developed nuclear
weapons so today there are more than
10,000 or more than 11,000 nuclear
warheads on the planet and one slight
miscalculation can set off nuclear war
if that happens it's almost guaranteed
to to extinguish our
species and if we are the only
civilization intelligent civilization or
or only place in the universe that where
the is life then that is
frightening which means that human
stupidity can end all life in the
universe right so yeah so the
question the answer we don't know like
you said there are two possibilities
either we are alone or we are not if we
are alone then we have such an
incredible responsibility to continue
life in the universe and intelligent
life in the universe which is us and if
we are not alone well that itself that
too can be really SC which means there
probably are other life forms elsewhere
in the universe which means that some of
them could be more intelligent than us
which is dangerous which is very
dangerous because yeah that could be a
threat so
yeah uh Arijit says can we input
Consciousness in an AI we can't first of
all we don't know what Consciousness is
we don't have a definition of
Consciousness and to input something
into an AI we need to have it somewhere
now where is consciousness I know
there's a Consciousness here I know each
person I see has Consciousness and
intelligence I know cats dogs Etc have
Consciousness
horses every life form has some degree
of Consciousness but what is
consciousness how do I physically
localize it how do I transfer it from
one place to another I don't
know so we don't have the means to do
that we don't even have any
understanding of what Consciousness is
we don't have a definition of
Consciousness so as of today we cannot
do
it do not ask me questions about history
today my dear friends we'll we'll take
it in the history live stream history
geopolitics live
stream all right
um okay Ric says do we need different
types of physics to reach ala centor it
depends on how quickly you want to reach
there let's say you want to reach Alpha
centor in 100 years so how far is Alpha
centor or Proxima centor from here it's
4 point something light years away which
means if I shine a laser beam at at that
star system it's going to take four
point something less than five years to
reach there but if you want to travel in
a standard rocket let's say the Space X
Starship to Alpha centor it's going to
take you more than 100,000 years to
reach there more than than 100,000 years
at that
speed so you will reach there but you
will reach there in 100,000 years who
wants to take that long it's going to be
God knows how many human Generations if
it's four generations in a
century
okay and 10 centuries is thousand years
so that's 40
Generations 10,000 is 400 so 4,000
Generations will go by roughly for
100,000 years that's that's ridiculous
so let's say you want to reach in 50
years how do you do that do you need
different types of physics different
kinds of physics no physics will remain
the same but you will need different
technology you'll probably need to
accelerate your vehicle your spacecraft
to a certain to relativistic speeds
which means speeds that are comparable
to the speed of light let's say 0.1 C
0.2c we see the speed of
light to do that you will need to use
different technology not the chemical
rocket technology that we have today you
would probably need to use light sale
technology and there is
a project underway which could become
operational in a decade or two which is
called breakthrough starshot if I'm not
mistaken so they plan to make these
solar sale equipped micro spacecraft
which will be accelerated to
relativistic speeds towards Alpha centor
Proxima centor
using radiation pressure so radiation
and light itself can exert
pressure on on and if you have a large
enough object like a light sail which is
extremely thin you can use sunlight
itself or any other light to accelerate
that spacecraft so you use that you use
this micro spacecraft with light sails
and you shine laser beams on that it's
going to accelerate that to relativistic
velocities and then those micro
spacecraft can reach Proxima centor in
20 30 years
that is feasible with today's technology
almost there we almost there we would
need gigawatt lasers which we will shine
from the surface of the Earth onto the
spacecraft So within a decade or two we
may be there we may have the technology
so you need new technology not new
physics to reach Alpha centor in a
reasonable time
frame so we will already we will soon be
in a position to send robotic spacecraft
to Alpha
centor in a time frame of about 30 or so
years so the journey will take about 30
or so years okay but sending humans will
take longer because we will need a much
larger light sale and you will need a
spacecraft that can sustain
humans keep them alive for let's say 30
years on a oneway trip and then 30 years
on a on a trip back if you can do that
that's 60 or so years and so on so we
are still a little bit way off from
being able to do that first of all we
want to send humans to the moon and then
to Mars and then we can think of other
things so yeah you need new technology
not new
physics okay let's take a couple more
questions divata Shukla says are we in a
simulation or are we a 3D being
generated created by higher dimensional
beings so once again we don't have
answers to these questions because to
answer these questions satisfactorily
one way or the other we need data we
need empirical evidence that says oh yes
this this set of data points tell tells
us that we may be in a simulation so how
do we know that we are in a simulation
we have to perhaps devise experiments
that would indicate that there's a
simulation once a simulation it's like a
computer program we play these games
right PlayStation games today we have
PS4 we have Xbox whatever and 20 years
ago I mean I had a PlayStation 2 I
bought it a decade or two decades ago
when it was brand new it was it had just
come out I had a PS2 and the resolution
of the games wasn't that great but today
the PS4 or whatever it is these days the
resolution is much higher so similarly
the universe will live in has a certain
resolution and maybe with sufficient RAM
and sufficient whatever else competing
power you can create a
universe with this amount of resolution
in detail
and maybe it's the most parsimonious
hypothesis that this is a simulation
actually right so we could be in a
simulation it's actually possible it may
even be likely some people say it's
quite likely like Elon Musk and so on
but is it this way or that way is it a
simulation or are we threedimensional
beings created by higher dimensional
higher dimensional beings we don't know
to know we would need evidence we would
need data that's how science works and
we don't have it thus far so maybe we
can perhaps in the future devise
experiments that allow us to find some
data that could either prove this Theory
or falsify
it shag says why are big tech companies
putting biases in their Ai and chat Bots
why can't they make their AI unbiased so
what is algorithmic so this is a
phenomenon called algorithmic bias and
when we have machine learning Al
algorithms and all they whatever they're
going to Output to you depends on what
they've been trained on the data the
data set they've been trained on so
generally when you have an AI chatbot
like chat GPT 3.5 or whatever version is
out there today and other uh chatbots
like clothe or Gro or whatever they are
trained these are large language
learning models language learning models
trained on tremendous amounts of data
information text and images and whatnot
now whatever data you use to train this
AI system
the AI system is going to talk like that
and that data all that information
that's going to be the sample the sample
size and if that information is is
biased in some way or the other then the
AI will also be biased let's say you
feed the
AI
trillion uh let's say you you you
input one petabyte of English language
text into it
so English language text will have a
eurocentric bias when it comes to
historiography and all that and and so
on so it's going to it's going to
incorporate and embe those biases let's
say I me let's say I become a
billionaire and I create my own language
learning model and I input it only
Sanskrit
text it's going to be a Sanskrit
speaking Ai and it's going to have an
indoc Centric bias and so on so that is
algorithmic bias can you make your AI
unbiased it's very hard to make it
unbiased and sometimes you deliberately
make introduce biases into into your AI
so if you want to
well if you want to uh have your AI
conform to certain ideological standards
then you can program those biases into
it either by feeding it text and data
which is already biased towards that IDE
ideology or you can program some
constraints on top of whatever it's
already uh been trained on so you either
do it unknowingly or you do it
knowingly so yeah so every organization
every government every culture every
nation every civilization has biases and
has agendas and that's what is naturally
going to be seen in AIC sys so you do it
typically to further an agenda a
national agenda geopolitical agenda an
IDE ideological agenda a religious
agenda a racial agenda whatever it is
that's just how it
goes okay let's take let's say one last
question Tony Paul says why can't we
know what's out there Beyond The Event
Horizon of a black hole The Event
Horizon is the boundary between me and
the black
hole at which a light once a light Ray
crosses that a photon crosses that even
that light cannot come back come out of
black hole so the
boundary is the Event Horizon so why do
we not know what's beyond
that so if I an observer and I have a
black hole sitting in my lab and I want
to know what's be Beyond The Event
Horizon what can I do I can try and
shine a Light Beam at it or some other
kind of beam but all of that whatever
I'm shining at the black hole is going
to be absorbed it will never come back
so it's going to remain dark that's why
I cannot see what's inside from an
observer's perspective that's the
problem I face from a theoretical
perspective general relativity tells you
that Beyond The Event Horizon inside a
black hole at the center of a black hole
there is what's called a
singularity a singularity is a region of
SpaceTime where the curvature of
SpaceTime becomes infinite
the density of mass and density of
energy also becomes
infinite now from a mathematical
perspective an
Infinity is a division by zero which is
unphysical which means it actually is
telling you that there is something
wrong with your
equations your equations are break
blowing up they're breaking down at that
point which means which tells us that we
need
to improve the theory of relativity the
Einstein field equations make them
compatible with the quantum world
because Singularity is it's a sing it's
it's an ultra microscopic region of
space essentially so uh that's what it
is so our Theory doesn't tell us what's
inside there it breaks down and gives us
an Infinity a singularity and from an
observational perspective because the
Event Horizon is the point of no return
we can try and a beam of light in there
and see what's inside we simply can't
that light will be absorbed it won't
come back so that's why we cannot know
what's beyond The Event Horizon of a
black hole firstly we don't have a black
hole in a lab secondly even if we had it
we could not shine a light beam of light
on it and see what's inside and thirdly
most importantly our theory is imperfect
we need a better Theory we need to
improve general relativity we need to
formulate a quantum theory of gravity
which incorporates Quantum effects with
which reconciles quantum mechanics with
general relativity then we may know
what's inside a black hole until we do
that we don't know what's inside a black
hole okay I think we have crossed two
hours okay let's take one one last
question dures says what's the
grandfather Paradox it's something to do
with time travel let's say time travel
is possible according to
certain Solutions of general relativity
Wormhole Solutions Etc Time time travel
could be possible so here's the Paradox
of Time time travel let's say there is a
guy who's 20 years old
okay and
he is gifted a time machine for his 20th
birthday so this guy is something wrong
with him okay he's violent and all that
so he takes the time machine he travels
back let's say 50 Years or or 70 or
whatever years and he goes back in
time and he meets his grandfather when
his grandfather is a baby six months old
and for some reason he kills his
grandfather and then he comes back to
the to the present day now so this guy
goes back in time and kills his
grandfather when the grandfather is 6
months old which means that the
grandfather is dead at 6 months and the
guy who killed the grandfather his
father could never have been born so how
does he
exist because his G died 60 years ago
and the father was never born so how do
how does that guy exist the guy who
killed the grandfather so that's the
Paradox of time travel it it causes a
breakdown of
causality causality the causal structure
of the universe cause and effect there
is no effect Without a Cause without an
underlying cause but by traveling back
in time you can create situations where
causality breaks down and that is the
grandfather Paradox all
right okay I think we are done for today
we have crossed two hours again so thank
you so much for
for all your questions I really
appreciate that and I will see you in
the next live stream which will happen
on Monday not tomorrow because I have to
be in Delhi for the Prime Minister
swearing in tomorrow so I will see you
in the next live stream on Monday or in
any of the live streams next week so
thank you so much for all your questions
thank you for your viewership I really
appreciate that and I will see you very
soon in the next live stream take care
of yourselves and as always don't forget
to keep raising your standards thank you
you bye